[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Twenty-six]
[第二十六集]
Mom, my brother is eating without permission
妈妈 弟弟偷吃菜
Tell him to stop
跟他说不许偷吃
Wait till dad comes back
等爸爸回来再吃
Dad's back
爸爸 回来了
Time to eat, Dad
过来吃饭
Dad, come and eat.
爸爸 过来吃饭
You are back
回来了
Just in time, wash your hands and eat
正好 快洗手吃饭吧
No
不吃
Someone pissed you off again?
又生气了
Something happened at uni?
学校里有事了
Let's eat then.
那吃饭吧
But the kids won't eat without you start first
你不吃他们都不敢吃
Why not
有什么不敢 饿了就吃呗
Zimei, Henian
子美 鹤年
If you are hungry, eat first.
你们饿了就先吃
Don't wait for me.
不要非等我
Make me look like a feudal parent.
弄得我像封建大家长似的
Where are you going?
干吗去
Don't interfere, I am gonna start writing.
写东西 别打扰我
And you say you are not the feudal parent
你不是封建大家长
I see you totally are
谁是封建大家长
eat
吃
Dad, come and eat
爸爸 快过来吃饭
sit down
坐下
Specially made for you, dumplings with chives and eggs filling
专门给你包的 韭菜鸡蛋馅
Wilson's intervention
威尔逊的介入
Temporarily hindered
暂时阻碍了
Japan pushing it's scheme on rights in Shandong Province
日本谋求山东权益计划的推进
But on the second day after
但在意大利总理奥兰多
Italian Prime Minister Orlando left the Conference
退出和会的第二天
Japan representative Makino Nobuaki
日本代表牧野伸显
seized the chance to talk
不失时机地突然发言
Insisting the only way to solve the issue on Shandong Province
坚决要求按照他的条件
is to meet his terms
解决山东问题
Otherwise, Japan will refuse to sign the peace treaty
否则日本将拒绝签署和约
And quit the Paris Peace Conference
和退出巴黎和会
The situation plummet
形势急转真下
Beijing Foreign Affairs Committee of the Republic of China
北京中华民国外交委员会
Chairman Wang
汪大燮委员长
America, Britain, France, Italy and Japan
美英法意日五国
They are holding a second meeting
正在召开二次会议
Discussing the Shandong issue
[陆征祥 字 子欣 巴黎和会中国代表团团长]
The request of Chinese representatives to attend the meeting has been rejected.
中国代表参会的要求已被驳回
From last night until now.
从昨晚到现在
We requested three times for a meeting with Wilson
我等三次要求会见威尔
Lloyd George, Clemenceau
劳合·乔治
Yet all been declined
克里孟梭均不得见
Please inform us of the countermeasure as soon as possible
请速告知对策
Cabinet Minister
总长
Shall we rediscuss the content in this message?
这份电文要不要再斟酌斟酌
Nothing to discuss here
还斟酌什么
Send it now. Go
现在就发 快去
ladies and gentlemen
诸位
We are at the end of our tether now.
我们现在已经山穷水尽了
There is only one thing we can do now
只剩下一个字
To wait
等
Mr. Zixin, calm down first
子欣公 你先别着急
take a break
休息一下
I'm like an ant in a heating wok right now
我现在就是热锅上的那只蚂蚁
I dont know which way I should march to for my survival
不知往娜儿爬才会活命
How on earth can I calm down
能不急吗
I understand
理解
But you need to be in a good condition now
您可要保重身体呀
If you break down
你要是垮了
we will only be stuck even deeper
麻烦更大
Respond from BeiJing
总长 北京复电
read
念
Seek for President Wilson's help at all costs
不惜一切代价求助威尔逊总统
Fine, no time for dignity now
不要脸了
Let's seperate into five groups
这样 咱们兵分五路
Go to the four exits of the conference room respectively.
分别去会议室的四个出口
And the elevator entrance in the basement, Tan Shou
还有地下室的电梯口蹲守
Whoever sees Wilson
无论是谁遇到了威尔逊
whatever you do, stop him
无论如何要把他拦下来
And inform me fast
并迅速通知我
Let's do it
行动吧
Go now!
去呀
My fellow friends
诸位
We have to do this
堵门吧
What kind of diplomacy do we have here
外交办到这个份上
Is this even diplomacy when we are blocking the door?
这叫哪门子外交
Dear President Wilson
尊敬的威尔逊总统
Please help us.
请您帮助我们
No matter what.
无论如何都要帮助我们中国
Mr Gu
顾先生
Let me be honest with you
我坦诚地告诉您
My second proposal.
我提出的第二个方案
was just rejected
刚刚又被否决了
President Wilson
威尔逊总统
Your Fourteen Points put forward
您提出的十四条和平意见
Has become a household name in China.
在中国已经家喻户晓
Hundreds of millions of Chinese
几亿中国人
Are eagerly looking forward to it
都在眼巴巴地盼望着
That right over might
您主张的公理能够战胜强权
I remain committed to the plan
我没有放弃公理
But whatelse can I do now but leave
但是我现在除了退场之外
President Wilson, you are capable.
威尔逊总统 您是有能力的
We fully believe
我们充分相信
and rely on American influence.
和依赖美国的影响力
General Lu
陆总长
Let me borrow a phrase from Chinese.
我借用你们中国人的一句话
If I had known this day was goinng to happen, I wouldn't have lived it
早知今日 何必当初
Had it not been for the Twenty-one Aticles you signed
如果没有你陆总长
In the willing agreement of Zhang Zongxiang
如果没有章宗祥手书的那份
Gentleman, I think we would be in a very different situtaion right now
我想无论如何
Mr.President
总统先生
Is there really no chance to fix it?
难道就没有希望了吗
It all depends on your own effort tomorrow at the conference
有没有希望要看明天
You are the last hopw
你是最后的希望
Gentlemen, good day
先生们 再见
Don't work too hard, Shaochuan
少川 辛苦了
How's the preparation going?
准备得怎么样了
Total mess
一团乱麻呀
Mr. Zixin
子欣兄
Do you think there is any hope for us?
您说 我们还有希望吗
hope
希望
Treat a dead horse as if it's alive
死马当作活马医吧
We will give them our dying kicks
就算是垂死挣扎
We must try, right?
也要去试一试 对吧
Shaochuan, you have to understand
少川 你要明白
This speech of yours
你的这个发言
Is our last hope to save ourselves
是我们自救的最后希望
Please
拜托了
Mr. Zixin
子欣兄
I've never understood why since the Republic of China
我今天才算明自
so many once ambitious people committed suicides
为什么民国以来
Today, I can see why
会有那么多的志士自杀
Shaochuan, I know.
少川 我知道
I put you on the spot.
是我让你为难了
If it was not for the guilt I have on my back
如果不是我背看
for signing the Twenty-one Demands
二十一条签字的罪名
Tomorrow's conference
明天的大会
I would never let you rush to the front.
我是绝对不会让你冲在最前面的
Come
来
you see
你看
I found your favorite stinky tofu.
我找来了你最爱吃的臭豆腐
Stinky tofu with bread, combination of Chinese and Western
臭豆腐配面包 中西合璧
Mr. Zixin
子欣兄
Thanks for your consideration
你有心了
Don't worry, I won't back down.
你放心 我是不会退缩的
There's still some time for me to get ready.
还有点时间 我再去准备准备
Shaochuan
少川
On behave of thousands of millions Chinese.
我代表万千的中国人
Thank you
谢谢你
This flavor is the best
还是这个香
Messenger
来人
Minister
总长
Send the message to Beijing
给北京发电
The proposal of five countries jointly administering ShanDong
国务总理钱 威尔逊总统
put forward by President Wilson
在大会上提出
on the conference
由五国共管中国山东的提案
was rejected again by Makino Nobuaki
被本牧野再次否决
Britain and France have acquiesced in Japan's proposal.
英法两国已经默许了日本的提案
America's intervention failed
美国翰旋失效
Tomorrow
明日我等
We will make a last-ditch effort at the conference.
将在大会上 做最后一搏
Despite all the efforts and works from the Chinese representative
尽管中国代表据理力争
that ShanDong shall be returned to China
要求归还山东
However, in 1917, the British and French government
但英法两国却以一九一七年
supported Japan
与日本签约所负的义务为由
On the grounds of the obligation of signed articles with Japan
支持日本
The British Prime Minister even said
英国首相甚至表示
If Japan does not join the League of Nations
如日本不参加国联
Britain will follow
英国当随其后
With Italy has withdrawn from the peace conference
考虑到意大利已退出和会
Pushed by his eagerness to establish the League of Nations
急于在和会上促成
Wilson, American President
成立国际联盟的美国总统威尔逊
who's worried that without three countries among the Big Five,
生恐五强去三而功败垂成
his scheme wouldn't be accompolished
乃于日本秘密达成妥切
Changed his mind and secretly reached an agreement with Japan
改变原来的保留态度
supporting Japan to acquire ShanDong Province
支持日本取得山东
Situation
情势
Hang by a thread
危在旦夕
Smell this, XinGang
心刚你闻
The grass is stretching.
小草正在伸懒腰
The air smells of spring.
空气里有一股春天的味道
Stop it, stop it.
别闹了 别闹了
I feel a little numb when I smell this.
闻得我这个浑身有点麻麻的
We are in the campus now
咱们是在学校里
We can't be too intimate
还是注意点啊
So what?
在学校里怎么了
Spring is coming
春天都来了
Spring should be like this.
春天就应该这样
It's not like we are dating behind everyone's back
我们俩是正大光明的
Now that Yannian left, I do miss him
这延年一走： 我还挺想的
Mr. Zhongfu now leaves me in charge of
仲甫先生现在把
The delivery and publish of New Youth
送货 发行《新青年》这块的事
It's all on me
全交给我了
I'm making real money now
我现在挣了钱
With deep pockets
可是财大气粗
I can send money to my family
都给家里汇钱了
The bitter days have finally come to an end.
苦日子总算熬到头了
Bailan, I will graduate in three months.
自兰 还有三个月我就毕业了
Mr Zhongfu wants me to work at the New Youth
毕业之后仲甫先生跟我说
after graduation
他让我去《新青年》
Be a peer editor
做同人编辑
and then
然后呢
He wants to recommend me to stay as a teaching assistant.
他要推荐我留校助教
We can settle in Beijing in the future.
我们以后可以在北京安家了
What about the two of us
那我们俩的事怎么办呀
Didn't you promise to take me back to Qingdao?
你不是答应我带我回青岛吗
Sure
回呀
Not only going back to Qingdao
不光要回青岛
I'll also take you to the trestle.
我还要带你去栈桥上看一看
What is the trestle like?
栈桥 栈桥什么样啊
The trestle is a long bridge.
栈桥就是一座很长的桥
It was built in the sea.
它建在海里
It goes more than one hundred meters from the seaside.
距离海边有一百多米
When there is heavy rain and high tides
然后等到风大浪急的时候
You mustn't go up there alone.
你可千万不能一个人上去
Otherwise, if you being not careful
要不然一不小心呀
you will be caught in the waves.
就被卷进浪里了
For real?
真的
Yes
对呀
What if I fall in?
那我要是掉进去怎么办啊
I cannot swim
我不会游泳
Well, in that case
你不会游泳掉进去
I'll stand on the trestle and laugh
那我就站在栈桥上看你笑呗
Watching you fluttering in the sea.
看你在海里扑腾
You are not gonna save me?
你不救我呀
No
不救
Really?
你真不救我呀
Really
真不救
You have to flutter in the sea.
你得在海里扑腾
to learn how to swim.
你才能学会游泳
You are so mean
你怎么那么坏呀
I dare you to not save me
你敢不救我 你真不救我吗
I won't save you.
我不救你
You have come to Qingdao.
你都来了青岛了
You can't stay not swimming
你不会游泳哪行啊
Something big has happened.
出大事了
what's up
怎么了
Something bad, really bad
出大事了 出大事了
Jianmin Jianmin, wait a minute
建民 建民 等会儿
Why are you running
跑什么
Something's wrong in Paris. Shandong is finished.
巴黎出事了 山东完了
go
走
Something's wrong. Something's wrong.
出事了 出事了
XinGang
心刚
Go, go, go, go
走走走 快
Where is justice?
这是什么道理呀
How can they be this unreasonable?
哪有这样不讲道理的呢
A bunch of promise breaking bastards!
不是出尔反尔的浑蛋吗
I see.
我知道了
I swore.
我 说了粗口
This is outragous
欺人太甚
At the Paris Peace Conference yesterday
昨天在巴黎和会的大会上
Wilson finally delivered a speech.
威尔逊 他终于发表了讲话
He's saying that China should accept it's unfortunate faith as it be
[李大钊 字 守常 北京大学图书馆主任]
And aproved Japan's plan.
而且同意了日本的方案
That ShanDong Province will be officially handed over to Japan.
要把中国的山东正式移交给日本
China's diplomacy has completely failed.
中国的外交彻底失败了
What is going on here?
这是怎么回事呢
Didn't you say two days ago?
前两天不是还说
There's hope that the five countries will govern Shandong?
五国共管山东是有希望的吗
How can that change in a blink?
怎么转身就变了呢
What's going on?
这怎么回事
Brother Zhongfu
仲甫兄
This is the good man in your words
这就是你心里那第一大好人
This is what Wilson did!
威尔逊干的事啊
This is rogue's behavior!
这是臭流氓啊
Imperialism is all hooligans!
帝国主义全是流氓
Now!
现在呀
It's not the endgame
还没有到最后的时候
Maybe there is still room for manoeuvre.
或许还有回旋的余地
Now we have to do our best.
我们现在要尽全力
To save something
去挽回这个败局
What Peking University can do
我们北大能做到的
Is to use all platforms and all means.
就是利用所有的平台和手段
Speak out loud what is Peking University's attitude to the outside world
向外界表明我们北大的声音
Show the society the clear stand of Peking University.
向社会表明我们北大鲜明的态度
We will never flinch.
我们决不退缩
To urge the Chinese government and delegation
来促使中国政府和代表团
Take the most effective measures.
掌出最有效的措施
To fight for the last time
去进行最后的抗争
Shouchang, Zhongfu, we can only rely on you now.
守常 仲甫现在只能仰仗你们了
Hurry to publish a special supplement to comment.
赶紧发表专刊 增刊 发表评论
We need to act quickly.
我们呢 要赶紧行动起来
good
好
Yes
好 好
I'm Cai Yuanpei
我是蔡元培
Get me Wang Daxie.
给我接汪大燮
By the way, Dong Xiu
对了冬秀
I want to take a suit with me.
西服我想带一身穿一身
You have to prepare two sets.
得淮备两套才行
All right
好
This time,
这次过去啊
there are many speeches and meetings.
演讲和会议都挺多的
Please bring me some more shirts.
帮我多带几件衬衣吧
I heard from Junman
我听君曼嫂子说
Everyone in Peking University is busy these two days.
这两天北大都要忙死了
Is this a good time for you to go out?
你这个时候出去 合适吗
The country and Peking University will be doing just fine without me
国家和北大的事情缺了我能行
But my teacher, Mr Dewey, he is coming to China
可是我的老师杜威先生来到中国
He can't go anywhere without me
缺了我他是寸步难行啊
Which matter do you think I should attend to?
你说我 顾哪头才好呢
This BeiJing is full of shenanigans
这北京城就是事情多
Not as peaceful as the countryside.
比不得乡下清净
You can be have your peace
你可以清净啊
I told Junman
我跟君曼嫂子说了
asked her to visit you when she is free.
让她有空的话多来看看你
I'm done eating.
我吃好了
I'll help you pack the luggage
先去帮你收拾行季了
good
好
The failure of the Paris Peace Conference spread all over the world.
巴黎和会的失败传遍世界
Chinese overseas all felt indignation in their hearts
海外华人义愤填膺
A large number of Chinese and overseas students poured into Paris.
大量的华人华侨和留学生涌入巴黎
Support the delegation, also put pressure on them
既是支持代表团 也是给代表团施压
They gathered around the residence of the Chinese delegation in Paris.
他们围在巴黎中国代表团驻地
Ask the delegation to refuse to sign the peace treaty
要求代表团拒签和约
Claim to defend ShanDong to the death.
声称誓死保卫山东
Down with traitors
[巴黎 吕特蒂旅馆]
Give us back Qingdao!
还我青岛
Return to us ShanDong!
还我山东
Down with traitors
打倒卖国贼
We want justice
还我公理
come on
来来来
Let's close all the windows
我们一起把所有的窗户都关上
Even if you build a wall
你就算垒堵墙
The sound is coming in nevertheless
这声音该进来还得进
Pretend to be an ostrich, bury your head in the sand?
头埋在沙子里 那不是乾鸟吗
So you are saying
那你的意思
Just open them all
干脆都打开算了
Keep it open.
开着吧
It's open. At least we can get some air
开着至少我们还能透透气
Don't you feel these sounds condemning us?
你们不觉得这声音扎心吗
Minister is here
总长到
We have become motherless children.
我们成了没娘的孩子了
Everyone, I sent a message to Qian Nengxun.
各位 我给钱能训发报
Request instructions
请求指示
He said
结果他回电说
He can't give it
他也做不了主
Asked me to go directly to Xu Shichang.
让我直接去找徐世昌
Okay then, I turned to Xu Shichang.
好 那我就去找徐世昌
Still haven't heard back from him
结果到现在我也没等到他的回电
Brother Zixin, what shall we do?
子欣兄 那我们怎么办呢
We can't resign and commit suicide altogether
总不能集体辞职 集体自杀吧
Shaochuan
少川哪
I really have no idea
我是实在没有办法了
I went to Wang Daxie for advice again.
我又去找汪大燮出主意
He told me the same thing as yesterday.
他还是昨天的那个办法
He asked us to make a compromise proposal.
他让我们搞一个妥协的提案
Go to Wilson,
去求威尔逊
Lloyd George,
劳合·乔治
and Clemenceau
和克里孟梭
Down with traitors and give me back Qingdao.
打倒卖国贼 还我青岛
Down with traitors
打倒卖国贼
Did you hear that? Did you hear that?
听见了吧 听见了吧
In a blink of an eye, we are traitors.
一转眼我们就成卖国贼了
Everyone, how can we even look at ourselves now?
各位 该如何自处
Give your opinion.
发表意见吧
I asked the Guangzhou military junta
我请示了我们广州军政府
The instruction they gave is eight words
得到的指示是八个字
Fight to death for every inch and right
主权至上 寸土必争
Strong words it is
说得真好听
Every inch of the land
寸土必争
You should ask him though
你该去问问他介
How shoudl we fight?
怎么去争
Brother Zixin, it's over.
子欣兄 事已至此
I think we can only try Wang daxie's way.
我想只能按汪天燮的法子试试
We cannot be that traitor
我们总不能做一群
sit here and wait for the end of us
坐以待毙的卖国贼吧
Shaochuan
少川哪
Wang Daxie made it sounds easy
汪大燮说得容易
Compromise. How can we compromise?
妥协妥协 可该怎么妥协呀
Where is the middle ground?
这中间的尺度和分寸
Is extremely difficult to negotiate
是极难把握的
The word traitor
卖国贼这几个字
It's too heavy
很沉哪
If it goes wrong
搞不好
We might as well pick up this title
我们自己就把这个称号
with our own hands
给坐实了
Everyone, as for now
诸位 我以为现在
We can't think about personal reputation anymore.
我们不能再考虑个人名声了
Our country has come to the point of the return
国家到了这个时候
We have to fight with all we have
我们唯有奋力一搏
I shall dedicate myself to the interests of the country in life and death irrespective of personal weal and woe
苟利国家生死以
Exactly
说得好
Good point
好
No space for worry and fear
不要再有什么顾虑了
This is our last duty
就算是最后的担当吧
Go upstairs now.
现在就上楼
let's go over every detail
一条一条地议
News! fourteen equals zero.
号外号外十四等于零
Wilson invented a new mathematical formula.
威尔逊发明一个新的数学公式
Fourteen equals zero.
十四等于零
Come and see, come and buy.
快来看 快来买啊
Wilson's newly invented mathematical formula
威尔逊新发明的数学公式
Shizhi, are you leaving Peking University at this time?
适之 你这个时候要离开北大
is it all right?
好不好
People will use this against you
这样容易授人以柄啊
Sir, I've been thinking about this too.
先生 这件事情我也是思虑再三
I have to do this
不得已而为之的
Mr Dewey' visit to China this time
杜威先生他这次的访华日程
It was decided long ago
是早就定下来
Already arranged.
早就安排好的
If I don't go
如果我不去的话
There may be some obstacles
可能有些事情
Things won't be so smooth.
办得不会那么顺利
Unless
那除非就是
This visit to China is cancelled
取消他这次的访华计划了
Dewey's visit to China is no small matter.
杜威访华呢 不是一件小事
However
可是我心里呀
I have this feeling that something serious will happen to Peking University.
总担心北大要出大事啊
Don't worry too much, sir.
先生 您也别太着急
It can't be that bad
不会出什么大事的
As long as we know cleary where we stand
只要我们摆正自己的位置
We can't count on one Peking University to shake the whole world
不要以为有了北大
It won't be like that
就能包打天下
Think about this, Sir
你想先生
Will Paris Peace Conference take orders from Peking University?
巴黎和会它会听咱们北大的吗
No
不会的
All we need to do is to make our attitude clear
只要咱们表明自己的态度
and try our best
尽力了就是了
This is about the fate of the country.
这事关国家的命运哪
I'm afraid it's not as simple as you think.
怕是没有你想的这么简单哦
I can tell
我知道
Now your mind is not about Peking University.
你现在心思已经不在北大了
That's fine, you can go
好你走吧
Sir
先生
Mr. Shizhi
适之先生
I hope you come back as soon as possible
我希望你能早去早回
If something really happens.
要是真出了大事
I will go and get you back
我还是要把你回来的
I don't have many helpers around me
我身边没有帮手啊
After You leave, it's only Zhongfu and Shouchang
你走了就剩下仲甫和守常两个人
Three leaders of new culture
你们几个新文化的主力
but one is missing.
缺了一个
Won't be as powerfull without you
这力量就 就小了呀
Sir, do you know what worries me the most?
先生 您知道我最担心什么吗
Speaking of Zhongfu,
您说到仲甫
What worries me most is him.
我最担心的就是他
You know him.
他这个人您了解
He is over confident and sometimes grumpy
做事一向刚自用脾气暴躁
He tends to go too far when things are tricky
遇事容易走极端
It might lead to serious problem
搞不好会捕娄子的
So I invited him to come with me to Shanghai
所以这次我去上海
But he refused
可是他不愿意去
Mr. Shizhi, you are too young
适之先生 你还是年轻啊
You don't know Zhongfu well enough
你不了解仲甫
He must be with Shouchang at this moment.
此时此刻他一定和守常在一起的
Shizhi
适之啊
Sir
先生
Go and come back soon
早去早回
Don't worry, I will, Sir
放心先生 我早去早回
Down with traitors and give us back Qingdao.
打倒卖国贼 还我青岛
Rutang
儒堂
Give me that file you have
你把你手里那个文件给我一下
Ok
好
Here
给
I've always felt that this wording here can be changed
我一直觉得他这个措辞
It's better to go with this
还不如上这个
Indeed
是应该上这个
Isn't it
是吧
Do what Shaochuan said.
按少川说的来
All right
好好
Down with traitors and give us back Shandong.
打倒卖国贼 还我山东
Give us back Qingdao, give us back Qingdao.
还我青岛 还我青岛
Let's eat first, everyone.
各位 先吃饭吧
The hotel was blocked by protesters.
旅馆 被抗议者堵死了
Can't go shopping now
现在出不去买东西
Let's make do with it.
大家就将就点吧
LaoYue
老岳啊
Later
一会儿
You have to ask those petitioners at the door to leave
你得把门口那些请愿的人弄走啊
Otherwise, we can't get out.
要不然可出不去了
That'd be impossible
弄是弄不走了
Just today
今天我一天哪
I met with 16  groups of Chinese representatives
就接待了十六拨华人代表
Those people around the hotel now?
现在旅馆周围的人哪
It will only be more of them coming
是有增无减哪
what shall we do then
那怎么办
I asked the hotel for a car
我联系了旅馆一辆小轿车
Only three people can get in except the driver
除了司机外呢 只能坐三个人
It's parked in a garage facing the street in the backyard
这辆车就停在后院临街的车库里
Quiet area
那个地方偏假
Few people there, it's safe
没什么人 绝对安全
So be it
好吧
Shaochuan Shaochuan
少川 少川
I can't live without your stinky tofu now
我都快离不开你的臭豆腐了
General Lu
陆总长
Everyone
各位
Everybody!
各位各位
Chinese delegation to President Wilson of the United States
中国代表团致美国总统威尔逊
Prime Minister of the UK
英国首相
Lloyd George
劳合·乔治
And French Prime Minister Clemenceau's compromise plan
和法国总理克里孟梭的妥协方案
It's already printed
已经打印出来了
Come, take a look
来  看看
We did this with the name of traitor on our head
这可是我们冒着天大的罪名
Four compromise schemes, every detail checked and discussed
逐条议出来的四条妥协方案
If there is no second opinion
如果大家没有异议的话呢
Myself, with Shaochuan and Rutang
我跟少川 儒堂
will visit the heads of the three countries one by one
逐一去拜会三国首脑
try to win their sympathy and support
争取他们的同情跟支持
If this scheme can't be accepted
如果这个方案还不能被接受
Then I am afraid
那我们就只能
We can only wait for the doomsday to come
等死了
Shandong Province is the cradle of Chinese civilization
山东省是中华文明的摇篮
It is the birthplace of Confucius and Mencius
是孔子和孟子的诞生地
It is a holy place for Chinese people
是中国人的圣地
We hope that through diplomatic means
我们希望通过外交手段
China's interests can be preserved
保全中国的利益
Please help us
请您帮助我们
Nice to see you
很高兴见到您
A pleasure to meet
幸会
me too
我也是
Nice to see you
很高兴见到您
Pleasure is mine
幸会
General Lu
陆总长
I have conveyed your message three times
我已经第三次向威尔逊总统
to President Wilson
转达了您的意思了
He is not available to meet you tonight
总统今晚实在没有时间与您交谈
He said that you leave the files
他说请您把文件留下
and he will read it later
他一定安排时间仔细阅读
Then please give this to President Wilson
那请您把这个转交给威尔逊总统
If there is any doubt
如果有任何疑问
You can call me anytime
可以随时打电话叫我来
Please tell him
烦劳您转告他
that tonight
就说今天晚上
The three of us will stay by the telephone all night
我们三个会彻夜守在电话机旁
I'll hand it over to the president
我一定转交给总统
Sorry, General Lu
对不起 陆总长
I have conveyed your requests three times already
我已经第三次转达了您的意思了
Unfortunately
很遗憾
Prime Minister Lloyd George
劳合·乔治首相
cannot see you tonight
今晚实在没有时间与您交谈
However
但是
He said you can leave the document
他说 请您把文件留下
He will find time to read it carefully
他一定安排时间仔细阅读
Then please
那就请你把这个
Bring it to Prime Minister
转交给劳合·乔治首相
No matter what doubts you have
不管有任何疑问
You can call me anytime
可以随时打电话叫我来
Please tell him
还烦劳您转告他
The three of us
就说我们三个
Will stay up all night tonight
今夜会彻夜不眠
Stay by the phone always
一直守在电话机旁
Yes, I understand
好的 我明白了
I will make sure that the Prime Minister gets the document
我会确保首相收到这份文件
General Lu
对不起 陆总长
I have conveyed your messages three times
我已经第三次转达了您的意思了
Regrettably
很遗憾
Prime Minister Clemenceau is not available to meet you tonight
克里孟梭总理
He said please leave the document
他说请您把文件留下
He will read it carefully
他一定安排时间仔细阅读
Then please
那就烦劳您把这个
Give it to Prime Minister Clemenceau
转交给克里孟梭总理
If he has any question at all
如果他有任何疑问
please call me anytime
可以随时打电话叫我来
Please tell him
烦劳您转告他
The three of us
就说我们三个
will stay by the telephone all night tonight
今天晚上彻夜会守在电话机旁
Rest assured
请放心
We've been Paris this long
来巴黎这么久
I still haven't been to the Arc de Triomphe yet
还没去过凯旋门呢
Do you know what this Arc de Triomphe is for?
你知道这凯旋门是干什么的吗
For a state funeral
举行国葬用的
The funerals of Napoleon and Hugo
当年拿破仑和雨果的葬礼
Held there
在这儿举行的
I heard that the French have a motion recently
听说最近法国人有个动议
To have a memorial here
要在这儿点燃纪念
The ever-burning lamp of the unknown martyr who died in the European war
欧战牺牲的无名烈士的长明灯
Mr.Zixin, what do you say
子欣公 你说咱们三个
Will three of us qualified
有没有资格
to have a funeral here
在这儿办个葬礼
Buried in the ground or scattered into the water?
你说这土葬呢 还是水葬
I say cremated should do
要不然火葬得了
Shaochuan, let me ask you something
少川 我问你一句
When you first came to Paris
当初你来巴黎的时候
Have you ever thought about how you will be welcomed when going back?
有没有想过怎么回去
Mr.Zixin
子欣兄
I once saw it, like a dream
我曾经恍恍惚惚地看到
that the Qianmenlouzi in Beijing
北京的前门楼子
turned into the Arc de Triomphe
变成了凯旋门
And there is us, walking through
咱们几个人 穿门而过啊
People there waiting for us, cheering up for us
万众欢腾啊
huge crowds of people
人山人海
The elders, the kids
有老人 有孩子
You can hear them shouting out our names
万众欢呼着我们的名字呀
Lu Zhengxiang! Gu Weijun! Wang Zhengting!
陆征祥 王正廷 顾维钧
The drums and the gongs, the fircrackers and laughters
锣鼓震天 鞭炮齐鸣
That's not all
这个时候啊
From the crowd
这人群里边
A little boy running towards me
跑出个小男孩
He lit a firecracker
他还点着了一挂鞭炮
A huge one
那挂鞭炮
The bang sound from that one can go on forever
不说一千头也有八百头
He threw it close to my feet
点着就扔我脚底下了
It exploded at such close distance
炸呀 围着我炸
I jumped, trying to avoid it
我就左躲右躲
But I couldn't
那鞭炮皮崩着我了
It hurt, a lot
那疼啊
Then I woke up.
然后我就醒了
I was there, half awaken for a while
我缓了半天的神儿
Finally, realized it's no more than a dream
才发现是个梦
You two
二位
It's all my fault
对不起
I got you into trouble.
我连累了你们啊
it is me.
是我
I took your Arc de Triomphe
把你们的凯旋门
turned it to a pillar of shame
变成了耻辱柱
I'm sorry
对不起
So sorry
对不起 对不起
April 30th, 1919
一九一九年四月三十日
U.S., Britain and France hold trilateral meeting in Paris.
英法美在巴黎举行三国会议
Japanese representatives were invited to attend.
日本代表应邀出席
This meeting set the final terms for
会议议定了巴黎和会
Provisions on the ShanDong issue discussed on the Paris Peace Conference
关于山东问题的条款
The three great power finally made a decision
英法美三强终于做出决定
Agreed that all the rights and interests of Germany in Shandong
同意将德国在山东的所有权益
will be transfered to Japan
转让给日本
China
中国
We are the ones that won this war
作为一个战胜国
And all we got is a treaty like this?
应该得到这样一个
A treaty that disgraces the country?
丧权辱国的条约吗
This is a disgrace to mankind
这是人类的耻辱
It is an unprecedented shame
是亘古未有的奇耻大辱
Our Chinese government
我们中国政府
refuse to accept this.
拒绝接受这个
This shameful peace treaty
可耻的和约
I'm Wang Daxie.
我是汪大燮
We lost ShanDong
伯公 山东丢了
Chen lu
[汪大燮 字伯棠 中华民国外交委员会委员长]
You are the acting foreign minister.
你堂堂代理外交总长
Are you gonna just cry at time like this?
在这个时候哭什么哭
What the hell happened?
到底发生了什么事
Make it clear to me.
你给我说清楚
Shandong is lost.
山东丢了
We lost. We lost completely.
我们输了 我们彻底输了
We became the one lost now
现在变成了输家
You and I, we will never be able to face our people again
你我 何颜以对国人哪